I guess with me too and all this focus
on men's behavior what's strange is how
similar it feels to the 1970s where what
forty years on the original men's
movement that the way that the women's
movement and feminism has kind of given
women consciousness and men need to step
up and respond to it feels very very
contemporary feels like it could have
been written yesterday yeah so it feels
like we're in the same yes thing and
it's kind of led by women coming out and
finding their voice in addressing and
challenging the masculine and what's
sometimes called the patriarchy or
patriarchal behavior or unconscious
things in the mail maybe even set or
kind of kick-started a little bit by at
the political situation by somebody like
Trump being elected I don't know what
all the factors that bring it up right
now but it's I'm happy that it comes up
you know it's great for women to really
speak up and to tell the truth and with
the meet you thing and you know to not
swallow it and the level of denial
that's been there for so long it's
really exposed right now what you know
so many men have presumed is okay it's
just not okay and so there's a real like
whoa gotta check myself out that's
really great and then that brings a
response from the men but if we come
back with like oh my god it's terrible
person and I'm a male and then you know
nothing can happen nothing good from
that space yeah I am let me face those
places inside of myself where I have
those distortions where I might be
misogynist misogynistic where I might
have unconscious you know sexual
projections onto women and look at that
and I feel like that's what we were
doing back in the 70s also you know that
whole concept of objectifying women was
completely unknown at that point our
thought about you really what oh yeah
god I do that
I do that all the time you know what
happens if I go into that and look at
how I do that does that change how I see
women and how I relate to women
yes it does you know but it's got to be
owned you know so right now we're being
called on to look again you know and
it's not to please the women though we
have to do it for ourselves because
there's something comes up and if
there's a reaction there inside to it
it's telling us something about
ourselves and to do it for ourselves and
how would you summarize the work that
men need to do in the simplest possible
way is it to really look at themselves
look at the distortions look at the look
at the ways that because what because I
say there's a kind of integration that a
lot of these negative behaviors of men
are are disintegrated parts of the male
psyche that on their own are very can be
very dangerous
like the aggression left to itself or
rage or any of these like there are
tools and they're part of what makes
like they're part of the male psyche but
they have to be integrated healthily
within within the personality that's how
I how I see it yeah well it is my
observation that most of the work that
men have to do on themselves has to do
with getting grounded in their
masculinity and most of the work that
women have to do on themselves it kind
of relaxed confident grounded in their
femininity and then of course we have
this inner polarity I have a feminine
side a woman as a masculine side but
those sides rather than be problematic
which they are and you're not relaxed
and confident in your biological sex
become very easy to integrate as well as
the external relationships with opposite
sex so it seems to me that it is my
experience that the work that people
need to doing themselves is to really
look at why do I not feel relaxed and
confident grounded in the mask and in
another word for that on the male side
was castrated so this there's a
castration wound usually that keeps man
from feeling that he's really got what
it takes you know to do the job and so
instead of being relaxed and confident
he's trying to compensate for the
feeling of deficiency in these efforting
and it brings him up and in this head
and you know turns him into a dickhead
and there's a lot of talk at the moment
about wanting men to be more vulnerable
like there's something definitely in the
in the culture now about men being asked
out from their open up to be more
revealing about their feelings but it
seems to me there's a kind of danger if
that's not balanced by some kind of
respect for the healthy masculine which
is which is more than just vulnerability
because that whole narrative sort of
feeds into an idea that men are faulty
masculinity is faulty there's something
wrong with with the masculine it's not
helpful for a man to go to vulnerability
if there's not a respect for the mascot
and to go to a kind of feminized
personality type out of a feeling of
guilt and shame for the mask on what the
masculine is done and what it's capable
of and all of that there is a lot of
horror shows that have happened from the
mess Khun Danai ibly but the healing of
that is not for the men to become
feminine it's for the men to grow up
embrace their masculinity face the
distortions that have been given to them
by the culture and by their families
face the castration this happened that's
taking away their confidence in their
power the personal wounding that's
happened and show up in presence and
then once in presence
boner ability isn't is wonderful and
it's man being in presence
what does that look like and what is the
work that gets us there as a man as men
the work is before I think going through
one thing is that collective place
that's held in the masculine where it is
really distorted and owning them and
that means facing your own personal
shadow and the collective masculine
shadow and the impulses towards
dominance and violence and anger and and
all of the horror stuff that's happening
in the world that comes from men is also
inside of me it's also inside of you we
all carry it we've all been imprinted
with it but once we face that and once
we
we feel how it manifests in us and we
allow herself to be courageous enough to
say yeah I'm carrying that and I go in
there and I feel it then I'm no longer a
slave to it I'm a slave to it when it's
operating from my unconscious when it's
operating out of my shadow so it's it's
the embracing of the distortion it's the
allowance of the strong masculine energy
to come through and and the irony of it
is that so many men have come to work on
themselves made a decision at some point
that they want to be anything but like
those guys you know pointing to the
family pointing to the distorted men in
our culture and stuff and so they reject
the mask and it's a kind of self
castration you know they want to be
anything but like that and they can feel
in sense that they have that inside of
them they have the violence they have
the distortion we have the aggression
and yet my experience is is that it's
not that big it's like it's a barrier
you have to go through and so I often
take men right into that in a really
strong way and encourage them to really
feel and and share and experience all
the aggression inside all the distortion
to own and to feel it to feel even the
tendency towards violence the
frustration that's there inside and when
they do that they come in to they they
go through you go through it and you
come into a relaxed place underneath it
which is really like the roots of the
mask um you know and that's what holds
the body afterwards but you can't get
there if you don't pass through the
distortion if you don't look at your
shadow if you don't own that stuff and
how it plays out in me and I find men
are very very kind with each other when
we share our shadow and we share our
distortion doesn't go to judgment it's
like it's relieving it's a cough yeah
somebody's talking about it thank God
what are the qualities of the healthy
masculine well a healthy mass come from
one has is grounded so this is present
about a man when he's in landed in his
mascot where he's it's it's relaxing to
be around him in a way because he's
grounded he's not efforting he's not
trying to be somebody he's not coming
from a place of deficiency so there's
this grounded presence that is as a
strong sense of discriminating
intelligence can see what's needed in a
particular situation and take action an
appropriate action without going over
his own boundaries and without
transgressing other people's boundaries
and we talk about the essence of
masculine the essence of feminine
sometimes it's very easy to say oh well
think of a quality like receptivity well
men should be receptive as well or women
can be strong so when you talk about
people sometimes get a bit touchy about
using the word masculine and feminine to
mean certain qualities what do you see
is the essence of the masculine for
example well I people do get really
touchy about that and and sometimes I
think that's really a pity because there
there there's an implicit judgement in
there and I'd offensiveness and that
whole thing you know it's like yes I can
be really receptive and soft and what
are typically called feminine qualities
but I think in that the essence and real
embodiment of the mascot it's different
it's just to say it's different than the
feminine is absolutely equal absolutely
equal in levels of power absolutely
equal and levels of intelligence
telchines absolutely equal down through
the whole list but completely different
you know and my embodiment in my and my
expression of myself as a man is
different than a woman in the feminine
and her expression through the feminine
and as the feminine but does she have
masculine qualities of course she does
and she can be as assertive strong and
you know directional as I am in when she
employs her masculine side when she gets
into trouble is when her masculine side
is dominating them
unconscious consciousness in running the
show same for me you know I can be you
know as integrated in some masks on I
can very easily go into my feminine
contact and and touch and love and
[Music]
nonlinear thinking kind of poetic
artistic side all that can happen but if
I'm not grounded in my Maskin and I'm
overwhelmed by my feminine then I come
out with a kind of distorted feminine I
become kind of bitchy and Moody and
withdrawn and hostile and edgy and
critical I mean it's like it's a swampy
moody or a shelf for a man to be
unconsciously possessed by a feminine
hmm that's what young called animal
possession exactly exactly and on the
other side there's an animus possession
when a woman is unconsciously possessed
by her mask on side it's it's difficult
you know she'll be very judgmental
opinionated she'll always know how
things should be and have no problem
telling anybody and everybody about it
and the problem though with animals and
it's judgmental-ness is that it's not
only directed outward to the outer world
it's also directed inward towards the
woman's own femininity and masculine
them can hold the feminine in a kind of
captivity inside and keeps it down which
is you know kind of ironically the whole
it's the internalization of the exterior
world situation and we're doing a
workshop in February to give people a or
to give men a more direct sense of some
of these qualities that we're talking
about what do you hope people will get
from that workshop a weekend intensive
process that they come away feeling in
love with being a man that they're just
vibrating in it they can feel it in
their bones they can feel
through the whole body and their their
unapologetic and unashamed and they're
connected with authentic vein of male
energy and they they don't feel afraid
of other men they feel trust in other
men they feel close with other men they
feel empowered they feel a sense of
self-esteem and I would hope that they
come out with a hint of some kind of
direction and purpose because I think
that's very important for for men just
to feel a sense of what do you really
want you know and so in a way you could
we could say this would be kind of like
going to the roots of the mass gun I
want them to have an embodied experience
because when it's really embodied and
you feel it there's just no denying it
you know and it's unforgettable